A Guide to the Robert Lee Evans Research Files on the Gochenour and Evans Families, 1930-1983
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Robert Lee Evans Research Files on the Gochenour and Evans Families, 1930-1983
Library of Virginia
33200
9.2 cubic feet (7 record center boxes and 26 card index boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mary Jane Evans Post, 14 July 1988.
Biographical/Historical Information
Robert Lee Evans (1906-1982) was born in Washington, D.C., and graduated from the University of Maryland with a degree in mechanical engineering and later from George Washington University Law School. He was a member of the Washington, D.C., Bar and the Bar of the U.S. Supreme Court. In 1919 he was employed as an Examiner in the U.S. Patent Office and later became director of the Physics Group. He retired in 1972 and died on May 11, 1982. Although interested in the history of his family from the 1930s, it was not until the late 1960s and early 1970s that he proceeded to gather the bulk of the information contained within this collection, organize it, and publish it in the work, History of the Descendants of Jacob Gochenour (Boyce, Va.: Carr Publishing Company, 1977).
Scope and Content Information
Although only one family history was published, compilations were also completed for the Henry Gochenour family and the Jeremiah Evans family, with indices to names contained in the histories. An unpublished manuscript on the Jeremiah Evans family is also included in the material. These family histories contain information sheets on family members. A specific number was designated for each individual according to his generation and place in the family (explained in folder 1 and placed in the container listing in parenthesis), and Evans would send out form letters requesting information or the verification of listed information. These would be returned with correspondence, notes, corrections, newspaper clippings, or other items of interest and were filed numerically in loose-leaf notebooks. Many contacts were made through the annual Gochenour reunion held in Woodstock, Virginia. Other collection material includes Shenandoah County marriage bonds, with an index, 1772-1850, and the 1850 census for Shenandoah County, compiled by Cleta Smith, who assisted Evans in his research.
Following the correspondence are Evans' research notes and card indices. Research notes, obtained from many public and private sources, relate principally to the counties of Shenandoah, Page, Rockingham, and Augusta, and contain Bible records, land records, marriage records, maps, and exchanges of information from various individuals. Folders marked "visits" are diary-like entries made during his travels to family members. Of particular interest are the notes on the Gochenour family collected by Philip S. Rhodes, a surveyor in Shenandoah County in the 1920s and 1930s, and notes on the Henry Gochenour family by Elaine Artlip, both with indices to the individuals mentioned. Also of note are Evans' annotated bibliographies that include a variety of sources pertinent to his investigations. There are also card indices to the baptisms and marriages listed in John W. Wayland, A History of Shenandoah County, Virginia, pp. 736-764, giving the names of parents and child, and age and date of baptism; to Shenandoah County names in Lantz Family Record by Jacob W. Lantz (1931); and an index to land grants from various sources contained within the material. The card indices in boxes 8 through 16 contain a partial index of the names found in Robert Lee Evans' History of the Descendants of Jacob Gochenour (Boyce, Va.: Carr Publishing Company, 1977). Boxes 17 through 19 house index cards for names located in the Jacob Gochenour notebooks. In boxes 20 through 22 are index cards pertaining to the names in the Henry Gochenour notebooks. Also in box 22 are cards related to the Jeremiah Evans notebooks and the land grants notebooks and loose papers. Box 23 also houses land grants note cards. Wayland's note cards in reference to marriages and baptisms listed in History of Shenandoah County, Virginia, are kept in box 24 and contain information on the parents, the child and the age and date of baptism. Boxes 25 through 33 contain alphabetized index cards for the Shenandoah County Marriage Bond Index, 1772-1850 and the Shenandoah County 1850 United States Census.
Organization
This collection is organized into the following series and sub-series: I: Gochenour and Evans family histories (Sub-series A: Jacob Gochenour family history, Sub-series B: Henry Gochenour family history, Sub- series C: Jeremiah Evans family history, Sub-series D: Miscellaneous); II: Correspondence; III: Research notes and card indices.
Contents List
- Gochenour and Evans Family Histories (Box 1-3)
  - Jacob Gochenour Family History (Box-folder Box 1 - Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Notebook I (Introduction - 139) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Notebook I (139A - 176) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Notebook II (1311 - 149A2) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Notebook II (149A3 - 1765) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Notebook III (13,621 - 14,9A69) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Notebook III (14,9A71 - 17,562) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Notebook IV (136,211 - 138,461) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Notebook IV (138,463 - 149A,534) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Notebook IV (149A,535 - 156,273) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Notebook V (156,281 - 173,235) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Notebook VI (1,321,171 - 1,366,635) (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Notebook VII (1,366,711 - 1,368,133) (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Notebook VII (1,369,111 - 1,3C7,742) (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Notebook VII (1,39C7,751 - 1,49A2,166) (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Notebook VIII (1,515,311 - 1,521,332) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Notebook VIII (1,521,333 - 1,562,633) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Notebook IX (1,562,821 - 1,562,546) (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Notebook IX (1,562,551 - 1,565,752) (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Notebook IX (1,565,753 - 1,732,344) (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Notebook X (13,621,1a11 - 13,663,542) (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Notebook X (13,663,543 - 13,668,721) (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Notebook XI (13,669,111 - 14,132,221) (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Notebook XI (14,132,412 - 15,454,442) (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Notebook XII (15,623,221 - 15,646,243) (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Notebook XII (15,646,621 - 17,323,432) (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Notebook XIII (136,212,111 - 1,411,321,131) (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Family Charts (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Henry Gochenour Family History (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 28-33)
    - Notebook I (Introduction - 23,625) (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Notebook I (23,625 - 29A4,111) (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Notebook II (2,311,111 - 2,9A41,111) (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Notebook III (23,111,311 - 23,116,19C5) (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Notebook IV (23,116,211 - 231,129B,421) (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Notebook V (231,143,411 - 2,311,613,421) (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Jeremiah Evans Family History (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 34-38)
    - Notebook I (Introduction - 15,214) (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Notebook I (15,215 - 153,524) (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Notebook I (153,811 - 15,612,29A2) (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Unpublished manuscript, The Descendants of Jeremiah Evans of Shenandoah County, Virginia (2 copies) (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Family Chart (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 39-42)
    - Shenandoah County Marriage Bonds, 1772-1850, with a list of corrected additions compiled by Cleta Smith, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Shenandoah County Index to Marriage Bonds, 1772-1850, compiled by Cleta Evans (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Shenandoah County - 1850 census, compiled by Cleta Smith (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Shenandoah County - index to 1850 census, compiled by Cleta Smith (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Correspondence (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 43-75)
  - General: 1951, 1954-1957, 1959-1963, 1965-1973 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - General: 1974-1980 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Adams, Barbara Enders: 1966 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Bennington, Cecil O.: 1959, 1966-1969, 1971-1973, 1975-1976, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Beydler family: 1868, 1906, 1963-1964, 1966, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Bly, Daniel W.: 1975 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Clem, Nellie: 1965 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Couchenour, Darrell: 1970-1972, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Couchenour, Ralph S.: 1960, 1962, 1978, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Evans, Robert Lee: 1930, 1936-1938, 1941-1944, 1955-1958, 1960, 1962-1963, 1966, 1968, 1970, 1972-1974, 1983, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Gouchenour, David: 1963, 1967, 1969-1970, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Gouchenour, Henry (concerning): 1969-1970, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Gouchenour, Howard: 1967, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Gouchenour, Warren: 1963-1970, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Gripe, Raymond J.: 1973 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Hardin, Warren J.: 1973 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Hockman, Noah A.: 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Howbert, Edgar C.: 1967, 1968, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Huffman, Diane: 1968-1970, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Ihrke, Leora: 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Indiana Gouchenours: 1945, 1972, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Lines, Jack and Louis D. Kork: 1963, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Maryland Gouchenours: 1958-1959, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Mennonite Library and Archives: 1973 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Pennsylvania Gouchenours: 1972 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Peters family: 1973 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Rader, Jacob K.: 1969 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Rockbridge County, Virginia Gouchenours: 1969 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Augusta and Rockingham Counties, Virginia Gouchenours: 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Ryman, John: 1965 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Seward, Dwight C.: 1967 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Smith, Cleta: 1962, 1965-1971, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Wilkin family: 1968 (Box 4, Folder 75)
- Research Notes and Card Indexes (Box 5-33)
  - Barr family (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Bible records (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Books (annotated bibliographies): Abbott - Harrison (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Books (annotated bibliographies): Harrisonburg, Virginia - Pen (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Books (annotated bibliographies): Per - W (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Branner, Casper (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Cemeteries (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Clarke County Historical Association - 1976 Proceedings (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - Coffman lineages (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Miscellaneous Virginia county court house notes (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Miscellaneous Virginia county court house notes (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Miscellaneous Virginia county court house notes (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Evans family (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Evans family (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Evans family (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Evans family (includes E. E. Macy notes) (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Evans family: books consulted (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Evans family: books consulted (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - Evans family: county court house notes (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - Evans family: Frederick County (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Evans family: notes from periodicals (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - Evans family: marriages and notes from printed sources (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - Evans family: other Evans families (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - Evans family: notes taken in Richmond, Virginia (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Evans family: visits with family members (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - Fisher, Foltz and Funkhauser families (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - Form letters sent: A - F (Box 6, Folder 102)
  - Form letters sent: G (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - Form letters sent: H - P (Box 6, Folder 104)
  - Form letters sent: R - W (Box 6, Folder 105)
  - Form letters sent (no response): A - F (Box 6, Folder 106)
  - Form letters sent (no response): G - K (Box 6, Folder 107)
  - Form letters sent (no response): L - Z (Box 6, Folder 108)
  - Gochenour data sheets (Box 6, Folder 109)
  - Gochenour family: Philip S. Rhodes' notes (Box 6, Folder 110)
  - Gochenour marriages (Box 6, Folder 111)
  - Gochenour, David: Augusta County, Virginia papers (Box 6, Folder 112)
  - Gochenour, David: Bible records (Box 6, Folder 113)
  - Gochenour, Henry: Elaine Artlip's notes (Box 6, Folder 114)
  - Gochenour, Henry: Elaine Artlip's notes (no indices) (Box 6, Folder 115)
  - Handwerk family: reunion booklet (Box 6, Folder 116)
  - Hite family: Elaine Artlip's notes (2 copies) (Box 6, Folder 117)
  - Hottel family: notes (Box 6, Folder 118)
  - Indiana Gouchenours (Box 6, Folder 119)
  - Jenkins family (Box 6, Folder 120)
  - Jordan family (Box 6, Folder 121)
  - Land grants (Box 6, Folder 122)
  - Land suit: Fairfax and Hite families (Box 7, Folder 123)
  - Land transfers: Abraham Gochenour (Box 7, Folder 124)
  - Land transfers: Henry Gochenour (Box 7, Folder 125)
  - Land transfers: Jacob Gochenour and Wilkin family (Box 7, Folder 126)
  - Land transfers: Joseph Gochenour (Box 7, Folder 127)
  - Land transfers: Levi and Christian Gochenour (Box 7, Folder 128)
  - Land transfers: Toms Brook (Box 7, Folder 129)
  - Land transfers: William Gochenour (Box 7, Folder 130)
  - Library of Congress (Box 7, Folder 131)
  - Library of Congress (Box 7, Folder 132)
  - Maps (Box 7, Folder 133)
  - Marriages (Box 7, Folder 134)
  - Miley family (Box 7, Folder 135)
  - National Archives (Box 7, Folder 136)
  - National Archives (Box 7, Folder 137)
  - Page County, Virginia (Box 7, Folder 138)
  - Papers that have been copied (Box 7, Folder 139)
  - Priest family (Box 7, Folder 140)
  - Register of St. Paul's Parish (Stafford and King George Counties, Virginia), 1715-1798 (Box 7, Folder 141)
  - Rhodes family (Box 7, Folder 142)
  - Richmond, Virginia (notes taken while in) (Box 7, Folder 143)
  - Rockingham, Virginia: 10th Regiment, Virginia Volunteers (Box 7, Folder 144)
  - Shenandoah County Geography Supplement (2 editions) (Box 7, Folder 145)
  - Skiles family (Box 7, Folder 146)
  - Surveying (Box 7, Folder 147)
  - Varner family (Box 7, Folder 148)
  - Visits (with family members): 1938-1978 (Box 7, Folder 149)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 150)
  - Miscellaneous Gochenour family information (Box 7, Folder 151)
  - Card index - Barbara Ann Gochenour to Frank Eschelman Good (Box 8)
  - Card index - Freda Irene Good to Carl Frederick Hockman (Box 9)
  - Card index - Carolyn Hockman to Marie Virginia Jenkins (Box 10)
  - Card index - Martha Bell Jenkins to Charles Jennings Long, Jr. (Box 11)
  - Card index - Charles Jennings Long, Jr. to Thomas Neher (Box 12)
  - Card index - Trelah Lorraine Neher to Florence Roberts (Box 13)
  - Card index - Gasaway Roberts to Ollie Louise Shuler (Box 14)
  - Card index - Ollie Louise Shuler to Evelyn Frances Thorpe (Box 15)
  - Card index - Evelyn Frances Thorpe to Stephen Michael Zobrist (Box 16)
  - Jacob Gochenour card index (notebooks) - Clara Abbey to Ivan T. Gochenour (Box 17)
  - Jacob Gochenour card index (notebooks) - J. Oliver Gochenour to Linda Dean Olsen (Box 18)
  - Jacob Gochenour card index (notebooks) - Catherine O'Neal to Ellen Zschaus (Box 19)
  - Henry Gochenour card index (notebooks) - Bessie Ackerman to Frank J. Gochenour (Box 20)
  - Henry Gochenour card index (notebooks) - Frank Gochenour to Carolyn Stillian (Box 21)
  - a. Henry Gochenour card index (notebooks) - Everett Stillian to Nancy Zungola b. Jeremiah Evans card index (notebooks) c. Land grants card index (notebooks and loose papers) (Box 22)
  - Land grants card index (Box 23)
  - Wayland's History of Shenandoah County marriages and baptisms card index (Box 24)
  - Shenandoah County Marriage Bond Index, 1772-1850 and the Shenandoah County 1850 United States Census card index - Conrad Abatin to James C. Bootes (Box 25)
  - Shenandoah County Marriage Bond Index, 1772-1850 and the Shenandoah County 1850 United States Census card index - Ann B. Booth to Elizabeth Coffman (Box 26)
  - Shenandoah County Marriage Bond Index, 1772-1850 and the Shenandoah County 1850 United States Census card index - Elizabeth Coffman to Sophia Fry (Box 27)
  - Shenandoah County Marriage Bond Index, 1772-1850 and the Shenandoah County 1850 United States Census card index - Stephen F. Fry to Rosenna Hitrick (Box 28)
  - Shenandoah County Marriage Bond Index, 1772-1850 and the Shenandoah County 1850 United States Census card index - Aaron Hockman to Catherine Klunedenst (Box 29)
  - Shenandoah County Marriage Bond Index, 1772-1850 and the Shenandoah County 1850 United States Census card index - Frances La Count to Hannah Pennywit (Box 30)
  - Shenandoah County Marriage Bond Index, 1772-1850 and the Shenandoah County 1850 United States Census card index - Jacob Pennywit to Jacob Sine (Box 31)
  - Shenandoah County Marriage Bond Index, 1772-1850 and the Shenandoah County 1850 United States Census card index - Elizabeth Quick to Daniel Snyder (Box 32)
  - Shenandoah County Marriage Bond Index, 1772-1850 and the Shenandoah County 1850 United States Census card index - David Snyder to William Witherall (Box 33)